<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="JoyfullNewesTransform_Kelly.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="JoyfullNewesStyle.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Joyfull Newes</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Florida State University, Office of Digital Research and Scholarship</publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">Attribution 2.0 Generic (CC BY 2.0)</licence>
            </availability>
            <date when="####-##-##"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>
               <p/>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Anonymous, trans. John Frampton.</author>
                  <title>Joyfull Newes</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Anonymous, trans. John Frampton.</author>
                  <title/>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="1580"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Authored in Microsoft Word and transformed using XSLT</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>herbals</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <front>
         <p><hi rend="capital">Joyfull Newes</hi> <!--there are A LOT of font changes in this one, how would I encode? hi? -->
            <lb/><hi rend="italics">out of the new found world,</hi>
            <lb/>wherein are declared the rare and
            <lb/>singular vertues of <choice><orig>divers</orig><reg>diverse</reg></choice> and <choice><orig>sundrie</orig><reg>sundry</reg></choice>
            <lb/><hi rend="dic">h</hi>erbs, <hi rend="dic">T</hi>rees, <hi rend="dic">O</hi>yles, <hi rend="dic">P</hi>lants,&amp; Stones, <!-- the letters are special characters but not at the beginning of the text, is this still DIC? -->
            <lb/>with their applicatons, aswell to the use
            <lb/><hi rend="italics">of <choice><orig>phesicke</orig><reg>physique</reg></choice>, as <choice><orig>chirurgery</orig><reg>surgery</reg></choice>: which being wel</hi>
            <lb/>applied, bring such present remedy for
            <lb/>all Diseases as may seeme altoge-
            <lb/>ther incredible: notwith-
            <lb/><hi rend="italics">standing by practize found</hi>
            <lb/>out, to be true.</p>
         <p>Also the portrature of the sayde
            <lb/>Herbes, very aptly described: En-
            <lb/>glished by <persName>John Frampton</persName>
            <lb/>Merchant.</p>
         <p>Newly corrected as by conference with
            <lb/>the olde copies may appeare. Whereunto are
            <lb/>added three other bookes treating of the <choice><orig>Bezaar</orig><reg>Bezoar</reg></choice>
            <lb/>stone, the herbe <choice><orig xml:lang="es">Escuerzonera</orig><reg>Scorzonera</reg></choice>, the properties of
            <lb/>yron and steele, in Medicine and the benefite of
            <lb/>snowe. </p>
         <p>Imprinted at <placeName>London</placeName>, in <placeName>Paules
            <lb/>Churchyard</placeName> at the signe of the Quenes
            <lb/><hi rend="italics">Armes, by <persName>William Norton</persName>.</hi>
            <lb/><date>1580.</date></p>
         <pb/> <!-- do multiple pages in between page breaks matter? (Not for now)-->
 <div type="dedication"><salute>To the right worshipfull Maister <!-- font size is bigger for this -->
            <lb/><persName>Edwarde Dier</persName><choice><orig>Esquier</orig><reg>Esquire</reg></choice>, <persName>John Frampton</persName> wi-
            <lb/>sheth much health, with prosperous and
            <lb/><hi rend="italics">persue <choice><orig>felicitie.</orig><reg>felicity</reg></choice></hi></salute>
      <p><hi rend="DIC">R</hi>eturning right worship-
         <lb/>ful, home into <placeName>Englande</placeName>
         <lb/>out of <placeName>Spaine</placeName>, and now
         <lb/>not pressed with the for-
         <lb/>mer toiles of my olde
         <lb/>trade, to passe the tyme
         <lb/>to some benefite of my
         <lb/>country, and to anoyde
         <lb/>idlenes; I tooke in hande
         <lb/>to translate out of Spanish into English, the three <!-- should landuages that are mentioned be encoded (not for now)-->
         <lb/>bookes of Doctor <persName>Monardes of Seuil</persName>, the learned
         <lb/><choice><orig>Phisition</orig><reg>Physician</reg></choice>, treating of the singular and rare vertues
         <lb/>of certaine <choice><orig>Hearbes</orig><reg>Herbs</reg></choice>, Trees, Oyles, Plants, Stones,
         <lb/>&amp; Drugges of the <placeName>West Indias</placeName>, for that the same
         <lb/>booke is of high commendation in <placeName>Spaine</placeName>, and o-
         <lb/>other countries, in such sorte, that in deede it might
         <lb/>bring in tyme rare profite, to my country folkes
         <lb/>of <placeName>Englande</placeName>,by wonderful cure of sundry great
         <lb/>diseases, that otherwise then by these remedies,
         <lb/>were incurable. And having finished the same
         <lb/>translation, I determined to dedicate my <choice><orig>travaile</orig><reg>travel</reg></choice>
   <pb/>
         <lb/>therein, to some rare lover of knowledge, for the 
         <lb/>worthinesse of the woorke: and not finding any
         <lb/>Gentleman of myne acquaintance, that was more
         <lb/>studious, and more delighted with learned works,
         <lb/>or that more cherished travellers, and lovers of all
         <lb/>good knowledge;determined to dedicate the same
         <lb/>to your woorshippe before al others, requesting
         <lb/>your woorshippe to accept the worke, and to be a
         <lb/>patron of the same, and to take it into your prote-
         <lb/>ction, since the matter is of good substance, and of
         <lb/>much value, and of me, truly and faithfully transla-
         <lb/>ted into English. And since the aforesaid Medicines
         <lb/>mentioned in the same worke of Doctor <persName>Monar-
         <lb/>des</persName>, are now by <choice><orig>Marchants</orig><reg>Merchants</reg></choice> &amp;others, brought out
         <lb/>of the <placeName>West Indias</placeName> into <placeName>Spaine</placeName>, and from <placeName>Spaine</placeName>
         <lb/>hither into <placeName>England</placeName>, by such as <choice><orig>doe</orig><reg>do</reg></choice> daily trafficke
         <lb/>thither, and that the excellencie of these Hearbes,
         <lb/>Trees, Oyles, Plants, Stones, &amp;c. have <choice><orig>bin knowen</orig><reg>been known</reg></choice>
         <lb/>to be so precious a remedie for all manner of dis-
         <lb/>seases, and hurtes, that may <choice><orig>happeunto</orig><reg>happen unto</reg></choice> Man, Wo-
         <lb/>man, or Childe, they have left of and forsaken
         <lb/>very much the olde order and manner of <choice><orig>Phisicke</orig><reg>Physique</reg></choice>,
         <lb/>which was used before that this was <choice><orig>knowen</orig><reg>known</reg></choice>, as
         <lb/>thinges not of so present remedie for all manner
         <lb/>of diseases, as these nowe late founde <choice><orig>owt</orig><reg>out</reg></choice>, are;
         <lb/> which by greate experience made in <placeName>Spayne</placeName>,
         <lb/> and other Countries, were throughly and <choice><orig>effe-
         <lb/> ctuously</orig><reg>effectively</reg></choice> prooved and experimented, to woorke
         <lb/>the effectes which are contayned in this Booke.</p>
         <pb/>
      <p>And thus, I leave your woorshippe to the Al-
         <lb/>mightie, beseeching him to gyve you long lyfe,
         <lb/>and for the Common-welthes sake that ad-
         <lb/>vancement, that your good nature, and
         <lb/>rare vertues doe wel deserve. From
         <lb/><placeName>London</placeName> the <date when="1577-10-01">first of Octo-
         <lb/>ber. 1577.</date></p>     
     <p>Your worships during lyfe to <choice><orig>com-
         <lb/>maunde</orig><reg>command</reg></choice>: <persName rend="italics">John Frampton.</persName></p></div>
  <pb/>
      </front>
     <body>
        <p><title type="head">THE FIRST PART OF
        <lb/>THIS BOKE TREATETH OF THE
        <lb/>thinges that are brought from the <placeName>Occidentall Indias</placeName>, which
        <lb/>serve for the use of Medicine, and of the order that must
        <lb/>be kept in taking the roote called Mechoacan, wherein
        <lb/>are discovered great secretes of Nature, and great
        <lb/>experiences: made and complied by Do
        <lb/>ctor <persName>Monardus</persName>, <choice><orig>Phisition</orig><reg>Physician</reg></choice> of <placeName>Seuill</placeName>. </title></p>
     <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="DIC">I</hi>n the yere of our Lord God,
        <lb/><date when="1492">a thousand, foure hundreth nine-
        <lb/>tie two</date>, our Spaniards were
        <lb/>governed by sir <persName>Christopher
        <lb/><choice><orig>Colon</orig><reg>Columbus</reg></choice></persName>, being Naturally born in
        <lb/>the countrie of <placeName>Genova</placeName>, to disco-
        <lb/>ver the <placeName>Occidental Indias</placeName>, that
        <lb/>are called this day, the <placeName>newe
        <lb/>world</placeName>, and they discovered the
        <lb/>first land thereof, the <date when="1492-10-11"><num>xi</num>, day of
        <lb/>October</date>, of the said yere: &amp; from that time unto this. they
        <lb/>have discovered many &amp; sundry laandes, and muche firme
        <lb/>land, as wel in that countrie, which they cal the <placeName>new Spaine</placeName>,
        <lb/>as in that which is called the <placeName>Peru</placeName>, where there are manie
        <lb/>provinces, many kingdomes, and many cities, that have
        <lb/>contrary and <choice><orig>divers</orig><reg>diverse</reg></choice> customes in them, in which there have
        <lb/>beene founde out, thinges that never in these partes, nor in
        <lb/>any other partes of the worlde have beene seene, nor unto
        <lb/>this day knowen: and other thinges which nowe are
        <lb/>brought unto us in greate abundance, that is to say, Gold,
        <lb/>Silver, Pearles, Emeraldes, Turkeies, &amp; other fine stones
        <lb/>of great value. Yet great is the excelle and quantitie that
        <lb/> hath come, and every <choice><orig>daie</orig><reg>day</reg></choice> doeth come, and inespecially
        <lb/> of Golde and Silver, that it is a thing worthy of admirati-
     <pb/>
        <lb/>on the great number of Melons,<!-- not sure if the right word here (will look back during proofing) --> which have come from
        <lb/>thence, besides the great quantity of pearles which have sto-
        <lb/>red the whole world: also they doe bring from those partes,
        <lb/>Popingaies, Griffons, Apes, Lions, Gerfaucons, &amp;
        <lb/>other kinds of Daukes, Tigers wool, Cotton wool, Graine to die
        <lb/>coloures with al, Dides, Sugars, Coppar, Brasill, the wood
        <lb/><name rend="italics">Ebano AMill</name>: and all of these, there is to great quantity, that
        <lb/>there commeth every yeere, <num>one hundred</num> ships laden there-
        <lb/>with, that it is a great thing, and an incredible riches. </p>
     <p> And besides these great riches, our <placeName>Occidentall Indias</placeName>
        <lb/>Doe send unto us many Trees, Plants, Hearbes, Rootes,
        <lb/>Juices, Gummes, Fruites, <choice><orig>Licoures</orig><reg>Liquors</reg></choice> &amp; Stones that are of
        <lb/>great medicinall vertues, in the which there be founde, and
        <lb/>have been found in them, very great effectes that doe exceeede
        <lb/>much in value and price all the aforesayed thinges, by so
        <lb/>muche as the copporall health is more excellent, and nece-
        <lb/>sary then the temporall goodes: the which thinges all
        <lb/>the world doth lackes, the want whereof is not a little <unclear>burte- <!-- can be beautiful, but it doesn't make sense here? -->
        <lb/>full</unclear>, according to the greate profite which wee doe see, by
        <lb/> the use of them to follow, not onely in our <placeName>Spayne</placeName>, but also
        <lb/> in all the world.</p>
        <p>And this is not toe bee <choice><orig>meruelled</orig><reg>marvelled</reg></choice> at, that it is so, for the
           <lb/>philosopher doeth say, that all countries doe not yeelde
           <lb/>Plantes and Fruites alike: for one Region yeeldeth such
           <lb/>Fruites, Treese, and Plantes as an other doeth not: wee
           <lb/> doe see that in <placeName rend="italics">Creta</placeName> onely groweth the <name type ="plant" rend="italics">Diptamo</name>, and the <!-- is there a tag for an emphasized word that is emphasized because it names a thing (put name and even type!!)-->
           <lb/> Incence onely in the region of <placeName rend="italics">Saba</placeName>, and the <name type="plant" rend="italics">Almaciga</name>
           <lb/>Onely in the Lande of <placeName rend="italics">Chio</placeName>, and the Sinamon, Cloves,
           <lb/>and Peper, and other spices onely in the Landes of the <placeName rend="italics">Ada-
              <lb/>luca</placeName>, and many other thinges you have in <choice><orig>divers</orig><reg>diverse</reg></choice> partes of
           <lb/> the worlde, which were not knowne untill our time, and
           <lb/>the people of olde time did lacke them, but Time which is
           <lb/>the discoverer of all thinges, hath discovered them unto us
           <lb/>greatly to our profite, considering the greate neede that wee
           <lb/>hav of them.</p>
       <p>And as there are discovered new regions, newe king-
           <lb/>domes, and newe provinces, by our Spaniards, so they
          <lb/>have brought unto us newe Medicines, and newe Reme-
          <lb/>dies, wherewith they doe cure many infirmities, which, if
          <lb/>we did lacke them, would bee incurable, and without anye
          <lb/>remedy: of which thinges although that some have know-
          <lb/>ledge, yet they be not common too all people, for which
          <lb/>cause I did pretend to treate, and to write, of all things that
          <lb/>they bring from our <placeName>Indias</placeName>, Apperteyning to the arte and
          <lb/>use of Medicine, and the remedie of the hurtes and diseases
          <lb/>that we doe suffer and endure, whereof no small profite
          <lb/>doeth follow to those of our time, and also unto them that
          <lb/>shall come after us: in the bewraying whereof I shall be the
          <lb/> first, that the rather the followers may adde thereunto, with
          <lb/>this beginning, that which they shal more know, and by ex-
          <lb/>perience hereafter finde out. </p>
        <p>And as in this Cities of <placeName rend="italics">Seuill</placeName>, which is the Porte and
           <lb/>skale of all the <placeName>Occidentall Indias</placeName>, we doe knowe of them
           <lb/>more, then in any other partes of all <placeName>Spayne</placeName>, for bicause
           <lb/>that al thinges come firsthither, where by better intelligence
           <lb/>and greater experience it is learned: so doe I, with practice
           <lb/>and use of them this <num>fourtie</num> yeeres <!-- in this case, would yeeres be included in num tag? -->, that which I doe cure in
           <lb/>this Citie, where I have informed my selfe of them, that
           <lb/>have brought these thinges out of those partes with muche
           <lb/>care,and I have made experience thereof with many and
           <lb/><choice><orig>divers</orig><reg>diverse</reg></choice> persons, with all diligence and foresight possible, and <!-- if you have done choice before on a word, do you do it everytime it appears in the same mispelling/old spelling? (divers) (YES)-->
           <lb/>with much happy successe.</p>
        <div type="subsection"><head rend="italics">Of the Anime and Copall.</head><p> <!-- from Sarah: You just need to make sure the end tag is at the end of the division -->
           <lb/><hi rend="DIC">T</hi>her do bring from the new <placeName>Spaine</placeName> <num>2</num>. kinds of Ro-
           <lb/>sine, that be both much alike one to the other, the one
           <lb/>is called <name rend="italics">Copall</name>, and the other <name rend="italics">Anime</name>. The <name rend="italics">Copall</name> is a
           <lb/>Rosine berie white, and of much brightnesse, it is
       <pb/>
           <lb/>brought in certaine great peeces, which are like too pee-
           <lb/>ces of <name rend="italics">Diacitron</name> very cleare, it hath and indifferent smell,
           <lb/>but not so good as the <name rend="italics">Anime</name>: with this <name rend="italics">Copall</name>, the Indi-
           <lb/>ans did make perfumes in their sacrifices, &amp; to the use there-
           <lb/>of was frequented in the Temples, by their Priestes.</p>
        <p>And when the first Spaniardes went to those partes,
           <lb/>these priestes went out to receive them, with little firepots,
           <lb/>burning in them this <name rend="italics">Copall</name>, and geving to them the smoke
           <lb/>of it at their noses: wee doe use heere to perfume with it in
           <lb/>diseases rising upon coldenesse of the head, in the place of
           <lb/>Incence, or <name rend="italics">Anime</name>: it is hotte in the seconde degree, and
           <lb/>moyst in the first, it is resoluative, and softneth by some <choice><orig>wa-
           <lb/>trish </orig> <reg>waterish</reg></choice>partes, that it hath.</p>
        <p>The <name rend="italics">Anime</name> is a gumme of Rosine of a greate Treem
           <lb/>it is white, it draweth neere to the coulour of Incence, it is
           <lb/> more oyly then the <name rend="italics">Copall</name> is, it commeth in graines, as the
           <lb/>Incence doeth, although somewhat greater, and beyng bro-
           <lb/>ken, it hath a yellowe collour, as Rosine hath: it is of a be-
           <lb/>ry acceptable and pleasaunt smell, and put uppon burning
          <lb/>coals, it doth consume very quickely.</p>
        <p>It differeth from our <name rend="italics">Anime</name>, that it is brought from
           <lb/><placeName rend="italics">Lenante</placeName>, which is not so white, nor so bright, insomuche
           <lb/>that some doe say, that it is spice of <name rend="italics">Charabe</name> or <name rend="italics">succino</name>, 
           <lb/>which is called Amber congeled, wherwith they doe make
           <lb/>Beades, but it not so, for that the <name rend="italics">Charabe</name> is a kinde of
           <lb/>Pitche, that is founde in the <placeName>Germayne Sea</placeName>, and it is ta-
           <lb/>ken out of the Sea in great peeces, with a dragge of Iron, 
           <lb/>so that it seemth to come foorth of some fountaines, into
           <lb/>the Sea, after the manner of pitch, and beeing come foorthe
           <lb/>unto the colde ayre, it congeleth, for becayse there is scene in
           <lb/>the same, peeces of stickes, &amp; other superfluities of the Sea,
           <lb/>cleaving unto it, and in this they shall see the errour of them,
           <lb/>that say that it is Gumme of <name rend="italics">Alamo</name>; and of others, that it
           <lb/>is of the pinetree.</p>
      <p> Of our <name rend="italics">Anime</name> <persName>Hermolaus Barbarus</persName>, a man most excel
     <pb/>
         <lb/>lenly learned doeth saie, that it is gathered about the place <!-- would this be encoded as said? (for quotes from other books: Quote) -->
         <lb/>where Incence is founde, and that lande on soile, is called
         <lb/><placeName rend="italics">Amintin</placeName> and therefore the thing is called <name rend="italics">Anime.</name></p>
      <p>That which is brought from the <placeName>newe Spaine</placeName>, is ga-
           <lb/>thered from certaine Trees, of a reasonable greatnesse, by
           <lb/>way of incision, as the Incence, and <name rend="italics">Almafiga</name> are gathe-
           <lb/>red: we do use thereof for many infirmities, and principally
           <lb/>for the griefe of the head, and paines therof, caused of hu-
         <lb/>mours, or of colde causes, and for stuffying in the head, that
         <lb/>thereof doeth proceede, after evacuation, perfuming there-
         <lb/> with the chambers in the Winter season: and where as are
         <lb/>generall infirmities, it doeth purifie and correct the Aire,
         <lb/>and they doe perfume therewith their head kerchers, when <!-- do you recognize this word -->
         <lb/>that they doe goe to sleepe: for them that doe suffer paines
         <lb/>in the head, and occasions thereof, it doeth profite to per-
         <lb/>fume the head of him that is so diseased, it doeth comforte
         <lb/>the head unto such as have it debilited, or weakened, and
         <lb/>doe suffer paines by occasion thereof: they doe put it also
         <lb/>in plaisters, and in seere clothes, where as is neede of com- <!-- go back to this (means dry, don't correct this to dry) -->
         <lb/>fort, and to dissolve, especially cold humours, or windiness:
         <lb/>they doe use it also in place of Incence, as well in the per-
         <lb/>fumes, as in the aforesaide.</p> 
      <p>It doeth comfort the braine, applied in the forme of a
           <lb/>plaister, and even so likewise the stomacke, and all partes
           <lb/>being full of sinewes, made after the fashion of a Sere <!-- same here just dry cloth -->
           <lb/>cloth with the third parte of Waxe: it taketh out the cold of
           <lb/>any member, whatsoeverr, being applied thereuntoo for a
           <lb/>long time, with refreshing it. It is hotte in the second de-
           <lb/>gree, and moist in the first.</p></div>
       <div type="subection" ><head rend="italics">Of the gumme called Tacamabaca.</head>
          <p><hi rend="DIC">A</hi>nd also they doe bring out of the <placeName>newe Spaine</placeName>
          <lb/>an other kinde of Gumme or Rosine, which the
          <lb/>Indians doe call <name rend="italics">Tacamabaca</name>, and the same <!-- is nationality, ethinicity be something to encode? (leave off for now!)-->
          <lb/>name did our Spaniard give it, it is Rosine
      <pb/>
          <lb/>taken out by incision of a tree, being as great as a Willow
          <lb/>tree, and is of a berie sweete smell, it bringeth foorth a red
          <lb/>fruite, as the seede of pionia.</p>
       <p>This Rosine on Gumme, the Indians doe much use in
          <lb/>their infirmities, chiefly in the swellinges in any part of the bo-
          <lb/>die, wheresoever they bee <choice><orig>ingendred</orig><reg>injured</reg></choice>, for that it dissolveth,
          <lb/>ripeneth, and marvellously desolveth them. And even so, it
          <lb/>taketh awaie any manner of <choice><orig>greefe</orig><reg>grief</reg></choice>, that is come of a colde
          <lb/>cause: as humours, and windinesse: this th Indians doe use
          <lb/>very commonly, and familiarly. And for this effect the Spa-
          <lb/>niardes hath brought it.</p>
       <p>The colour is as the colour of <name rend="italics">Galmano</name>, and some doe
          <lb/>say that it is the same, it hath white partes like to <name rend="italics">Amoni-
          <lb/>aco</name>, it is of a good smel, and the tail is like, insomuch that be-
          <lb/>in cast upon hotte burning <choice><orig>coles</orig><reg>coals</reg></choice>, and giving the smoke
          <lb/>thereof at the <choice><orig>nase</orig><reg>nose</reg></choice> of a woman that doth swoone, or els hath
          <lb/>lost her feeling by suffocation of the mother, it doeth cause
          <lb/>her to come quickely, and easily to her selfe. And the Rosine
          <lb/>putte to her navell, after the manner of a plaister, causeth
          <lb/>the Mother to keepe in her place: and the use thereof is so
          <lb/>much amongeth women, that the most parte which is spent
          <lb/>thereof, if for this effect, for that they doe finde themselves
          <lb/>very much eased by it, taking awaie from them all manner
          <lb/>of chokinges of the Mother, and comforting the stomacke.
          <lb/>Some that bee curious doe adde thereuntoo Amber and
          <lb/>Muske, and so it is better then alone. It is <choice><orig>alwaies</orig><reg>always</reg></choice> fixed,
          <lb/>without melting of it selfe, untill that it bee all wholie wa-
          <lb/>sted. </p>
       <p>And where it doeth most profite, is for to take awaie
             <lb/>any manner of griefe caused of colde humours and windie,
             <lb/>and beeing applied unto them in manner of a plaister, it ta-
             <lb/>keth them away, and dissolveth them with greate admira-
             <lb/>tion: it doeth cleave in such sorte, that until it hath done,
             <lb/>and wrought his effect, it can not bee taken away, and the
             <lb/>selfe same it doeth, being laide uppon swellinges, for that it
       <pb/>
          <lb/>consumeth and desolveth them, and if there bee any desire to
          <lb/>ripen them, it doeth it, and that very quickly.</p>
        <p>It is also a remedie verified, and experimented
           <lb/>that it doeth profite much in <choice><orig>Reumes</orig><reg>Rheums</reg></choice> <!-- are they saying rooms here?(rheums) -->, and Runnings,
           <lb/>wheresoever they goe, for it taketh them awaie, put-
           <lb/>ting a small peece a linnen cloth with this Rosine, be-
           <lb/>hinde both the eares, or the eare on the parte which run-
           <lb/>neth, for that it doeth restraine the running of them: and ap-
           <lb/>plied unto the temples of the head, in manner of a plaister,
           <lb/>it doeth withholde the runnings and the fluxe, that runneth <!--flux is a symptom-->
           <lb/>to the eyes, and to the partes of the face: it taketh away the
           <lb/><choice><orig>toth</orig><reg>tooth</reg></choice> ache, although that the <choice><orig>tothe</orig><reg>tooth</reg></choice> bee hollowe, and if therewith the
           <lb/>rotten <choice><orig>tothe</orig><reg>tooth</reg></choice> be burned, it maketh that the corruption goeth
           <lb/>no further: and being laide after the manner of a plaister in
           <lb/>the hollownesse of the necke, or griefe of the shoulders, it
           <lb/>taketh away the paynes: mingled with the thirde parte of
           <lb/><unclear>storax</unclear>, and a little Amber made in a plaister, for the sto-
           <lb/>macke, it doeth comfort it, and causeth appetite to meate,
           <lb/>it helpeth digestion, and dissolveth windines: after the same
           <lb/>sort put upon the moulde of the head, it comforteth, and ta-
           <lb/>keth away the paines thereof. In the Sciatica, or paynes
           <lb/>of the <choice><orig>hippes</orig><reg>hips</reg></choice> put thereunto, the effect thereof is greate:
           <lb/>and likewise it is so in all paynes of the <choice><orig>ioyntes</orig><reg>joints</reg></choice>: and in any
           <lb/>payne of the body whersoever, it be, chiefly if it come of cold
           <lb/>humours, or <choice><orig>mixt</orig><reg>mixed</reg></choice>: For because with this resolution, it hath
           <lb/>partes of binding, which doe give a marvellous comfor-
           <lb/>ting in <choice><orig>ioyntes</orig><reg>joints</reg></choice>, or in hurtes of Sinewes putting that a-
           <lb/>lone, it doeth heale and cure them, for greate is the expe-
           <lb/>rience, that wee have of it, <choice><orig>ingenderying</orig><reg>engendering</reg></choice> foorth with matter:
           <lb/>it taketh away an extreme colde: ordinarily it is applyed
           <lb/>to all griefes: <unclear>Adge</unclear> mingle therewith the thirde parte of
           <lb/>yellowe Waxe, for that will be applied the better, and the
           <lb/>use thereof is so celebrated, that the people knowe no other
           <lb/>remedy for any grief, but only the use of this Rosine, so that
     <pb/>
          <lb/>it bee not inflamations very hotte, and also in them after
           <lb/>the first furie is past, and the <choice><orig>fearcenesse</orig><reg>fierceness</reg></choice> thereof, it doth pro-
           <lb/>fite much for to dissolve the rest: it is hotte in the beginning
           <lb/>of the third degree, and drie in the second. </p> </div>
  <div type="subsection"><head rend="italics">Of the Gumme <name>Caranna</name></head>
    <p><hi rend="DIC">T</hi>hey doe bring from the firme Lande, by the waie
        <lb/>of <placeName rend="italics">Cartagens</placeName>, and number <hi rend="italics">de dios</hi>, A Rosin of the
        <lb/>colour of <name rend="italics">Tacamabaca</name>, somewhat cleare, and
        <lb/><choice><orig>thinne</orig><reg>thin</reg></choice>, called in the Indians language, <name rend="italics">Caranna</name>,
        <lb/>and this woorde and name our Spaniards have geven it,
        <lb/>and it hath in maner of the smel of the <name rend="italics">Tacamabaca</name>, although
        <lb/>it bee somewhat more strong of smell, it is very oylie, and
        <lb/>it cleaneth fast without melting, for the clamminesse that it
        <lb/>hath. It is a newe Medicine, and brought hither about a
        <lb/>tenne yeers past, and the Indians doe use it in their infir-
        <lb/>mities at against swellinges, and in all manner of griefes, and
        <lb/>now in our parties it is much esteemed, for the great effects
        <lb/>that it doth worke.</p>  
     <p>It doth profit and heale the same infirmities, that the <name rend="italics">Ta-
           <lb/>camabaca</name> doth, but ut woorketh more speedily, so that many
           <lb/>infirmities, wherein the <name rend="italics">Tacamabaca</name> doth not so much ef-
           <lb/>fect, the <name rend="italics">Caranna</name> doth easily heale. There was one that did
           <lb/>suffer paines in his shoulders, the <gap/> paines hee had suffered
        <lb/>a long time, in such sort, that he could not stirre his Armes, &amp;
        <lb/>having used a great time the <name rend="italics">Tacamabaca</name>, yet hee was not
        <lb/>healed, until hee had put thereunto the <name rend="italics">Caranna</name>, and there-
        <lb/>by in three daies he was made whole. In the griefes of the
        <lb/>Jointes, and the Gout <name rend="italics"><choice><orig>Arthetica</orig><reg>Arthritic</reg></choice></name>, it hath a marvellous ef-
        <lb/>fect, being applied unto the grief, so that it be not an inflam-
        <lb/>mation, of very hotte humour, for it taketh it awaie, with
        <lb/>much easinesse. In old swellinges, as well in humours as
        <lb/>in windes, it dissolveth, in griefes caused by refluxe or run- 
    <pb/>   
        <lb/>ning of cold humours or mixed, it worketh a marvellous ef-
        <lb/>fect: in all paines of the <choice><orig>Sinowes</orig><reg>Sinews</reg></choice>, and griefes of the head,
        <lb/>and griefes that thereof do proceede, it profiteth much.
        <lb/>Surely, it is a medicine to dissolve and to take away griefes
        <lb/>or great efficacie, and doth make his worke with great cer-
        <lb/>taintie in new greene wounds, especially of the Sinewes:
        <lb/>it doeth much profit, and greatly in <choice><orig>ioyntes</orig><reg>joints</reg></choice>, in the which I
        <lb/>have seene done only therewith very great workes: it is an
        <lb/>intercepting to staie the fluxe and running of the eyes, and
        <lb/>other partes applied behinde the eares, and in the temples
        <lb/>of the head. It is very fattie and oylie, and hot more then in
        <lb/>the second degree. </p>
    <p>And it is to be noted, that all these Rosines the Indians
           <lb/>doe gather by way of Incision, by giving cuttes in the
           <lb/>Trees, of which forthwith the licour doth droppe out, and
           <lb/>from thence they gather it.</p>
  </div>
   <div type="subsection"> <head rend="italics">Of the Oyle of the Figge tree of Hell.</head>
    <p><hi rend="DIC">F</hi>Rom <placeName rend="italics">Gelisco</placeName>, a province in the <placeName rend="italics">newe
       <lb/>Spaine</placeName>, they bring an Oyle or Licour,
       <lb/>that the Spaniards have called, oyle of
       <lb/>the fig tree of Hell, for that it is taken
       <lb/>from a tree that is no more nor lesse then
       <lb/>our fig tree of Hel, aswel in the Leafe,
       <lb/>as in the Fruite: it is the same that wee
       <lb/>doe commonlie call <name rend="italics">Chatapucia</name>, or <name rend="italics">Cherna</name>, it is also mil-
       <lb/>kish as ours is, for that it is more burning in the Indias for
       <lb/>the grosnes of the earth. </p>
   <p>The Indians doe make this oyle, as <persName rend="italics">Dioscorides</persName> doeth
      <lb/><choice><orig>shewe</orig><reg>show</reg></choice>, in the first booke, the xxx.Chapter, that is do pounde <!-- do roman numerals count for the num tag -->
      <lb/>the seede, &amp;seeth it in water, and after it is sodden, then they
      <lb/>gather the Oyle that swimmeth uppon it, with a Spoone,
      <lb/>and this is the maner to make Oyle of fruite and Seedes,
      <lb/>and Bowes of trees: It is verie much frequented and used 
      <lb/>of the Indians. As for expression or wringing out the <choice><orig>iuice</orig><reg>juice</reg></choice>,
   <pb/> 
        <lb/>they doe not knowe how to doe it, for lacke of knowledge,
        <lb/>this kind of oyle principally is better drawen out this way,
        <lb/>than by expression. This Oyle hath greate vertues, as by
        <lb/>the use thereof hath beene seene, and well in the Indias, as
        <lb/>in our partes, and all that I will say, is of very greate
        <lb/>experience, and much use thereof in many persons: it doeth
        <lb/>heale and cure all infirmities caused of cold humours, and
        <lb/>windines, it doth dissolve all hardnes with mollification, and
        <lb/>all inflamations being windie: it taketh away all manner
        <lb/>of paine in what parte soever it bee, chiefly if it come of any
        <lb/>colde sause, or windines, for that in this, it maketh a mar-
      <lb/>vellous woorke, dissolving greate windinesse, wheresoever
      <lb/>it bee, and especially in the belly: and with this they do
      <lb/>heale a windy dropsie, &amp; lykewyse al kindes thereof, annoyn-
      <lb/>ting there withal the Belly, and Stomacke, taking some
      <lb/>droppes therof with wine, or other licour appropriated, that
      <lb/>it may <choice><orig>auoyde</orig><reg>aid</reg></choice> the citrine water, and make the winde to be
      <lb/>expelled: and if they doe put it in any maner Glister, or Me-
      <lb/>dicine, given to it doeth <choice><orig>auoyde</orig><reg>aid</reg></choice>  out the citrine water, and
      <lb/>doth expell Windes with more assuraunce than any other
      <lb/>Medicine. In the griefes of the Stomacke of cold humors,
      <lb/>and windes, and <choice><orig>Colicke</orig><reg>Colic</reg></choice>, it worketh greate effect, anointing
      <lb/>therewith, and taking some droppes thereof, and principal-
      <lb/>ly they do this in that mostall disease called the <name rend="italics">Ileon,</name> which
      <lb/>is a cetrayne <!-- Look into this, strange word with slight errosion --> that purgeth at the mouth. It doeth
      <lb/><choice><orig>auoyde</orig><reg>aid</reg></choice> <choice><orig>fleame</orig><reg>phlegm</reg></choice> principally, in griefes of the jointes certain
      <lb/>droppes of this oyle taken with the broth of some fat foule,
      <lb/>it doeth empt away the humour that causeth the paine, it
      <lb/>doeth heale the olde sores of the head, that doth <choice><orig>yelde</orig><reg>yield</reg></choice> much
      <lb/>matter.</p>
   <p>A gentleman that did vomit his meate the space of ma-
      <lb/>ny yeeres, did anoynt his stomack with this oyle, and there-
      <lb/>with did recover &amp; never vomitted again: It doth undoe D-
      <lb/>ilations of the inner parts of the body, &amp; of the stomacke, &amp;
      of the Mother, anoynting it therewith. And unto yong chil-
  <pb/>
      <lb/>dren and Boyes, that cannot goe to the Stoole, anoynting
      <lb/>the lower parte of the <choice><orig>Navill</orig><reg>navel</reg></choice> with this oyle, it doeth pro-
      <lb/>voke them to the stoole: and if they have wormes, it doeth
      <lb/>expell and kille them, chiefly if they give them a droppe
      <lb/>or twoo with milke, or with some some sae grosse thing. And for
      <lb/>those that have lost their hearing, it causeth it to be restored
      <lb/>to them, with a marvellous worke, as it hath been seene by
      <lb/>many experiences. In griefes of Jointes, and in griefes of
      <lb/>swellinges, so that they come not of a very hotte cause, it ta-
      <lb/>keth them away and doeth dissolve them: any of the members
      <lb/>beeing drawen together, and annoynted with this Oyle,
      <lb/>they doe extende the Sinowes are mollified with it, ta-
      <lb/>king away the griefe if that there bee any: it taketh away
      <lb/>any markes or signes, whersoever they bee in the face,
      <lb/>principally, and the Morphe we which women many tymes
      <lb/>bee troubled withall, the anoynting with this Oyle, doeth
      <lb/>take it away, and consumeth it, not with litle content to them
      <lb/>that use it. It is hotte in the first parte of the thirde degree,
      <lb/>and moist in the second.</p> </div> 
  <div type="subsection"><head rend="italics">Of the Bitumen which is a king of pitch.</head>
   <p><hi rend="DIC">T</hi>here is in the Islande of <placeName rend="italics">Cuba</placeName>, certaine
      <lb/>fountaines at the Sea side, that do cast
      <lb/>from them a kinde of blacke pitch of a
      <lb/>strong smell, which the Indians doe use
      <lb/>in their cold infirmities. Our people doe
      <lb/>use it there to pirche <choice><orig>theyr</orig><reg>their</reg></choice> Shippes
      <lb/>withall, for it is well neere lyke unto
      <lb/>Tarre, and they doe mingle therewith Tallowe, to make
      <lb/>it pitch the better. I doe beleeve that this is <name rend="italics">Napta</name>, which
      <lb/>the ancient wryters doe speake of. <persName rend="italics">Posidonio</persName> sayeth, that
      <lb/>there are twoo fountaynes thereof in <placeName>Babylon</placeName>, one whyte
      <lb/>and the other blacke.  </p>
   <p>That which is brought from the Indias, we do use against
   <pb/>
      <lb/>griefes of the Mother, for that it doeth reduce the Mother
      <lb/>to her place. And if it rise on high, then put it to the <choice><orig>Nose-
      <lb/>trilles</orig><reg>nostrils</reg></choice>, and if it come down to the lower partes, putting
      <lb/>thereto a wet tent with this pitche, it causeth it to go up-
      <lb/>warde, to her place: and likewise it doeth profite, being ap-
      <lb/>plied to cold Infirmities, as the other Medicines do which
      <lb/>we have spoken of. It is hotte in the second degree, &amp; moist
      <lb/>in the first.</p></div>
  <div type="subsection"><head rend="italics">Of liquid Amber, &amp;the Oyle therof.</head>
   <p><hi rend="DIC">F</hi>Rom the <placeName>newe Spaine</placeName> they doe bring a Rosine that
      <lb/>we call <name rend="italics">Liquid Amber</name>, and one like Oyle that wee call
      <lb/>Oyle of <name rend="italics">Liquid Amber</name>, that is to say, a thing that wee
      <lb/>doe most set by, and as precious as <name rend="italics">Amber</name>, or Oyle
      <lb/>thereof, both of them being of sweete smell &amp; of good savour,
      <lb/>and especially the Oyle of <name rend="italics">Liquid Amber</name>, which is of sa-
      <lb/>vour more delicate and sweete than <name rend="italics">Amber</name>. A Rosine taken
      <lb/>out by incision from certaine trees very greate and faire, and
      <lb/>full of leaves, which are like to Juice, and the Indians doe
      <lb/>call them <name rend="italics">Ococol</name>. They carrie a thicke rinde, of the colour
      <lb/>of Ashes, this rinde being cut, doth craft out the <name rend="italics">Liquid Am-
      <lb/>ber</name> thicke, and so they doe gather it, and because the rinde
      <lb/>hath a smell very sweete, they do breake and mingle it with
      <lb/>the Rosine, and when it is burned, it hath a better smell, in
      <lb/>so much, wheresoever the trees are, there is a most sweete
      <lb/>smell through all the fields.</p> 
  <p>When the Spaniards came the first time, to that place
     <lb/>where it groweth, and did feele such a sweete smell, they
     <lb/>thought that there had been spices and trees thereof.</p>
  <p>There is brought much quantitie of <name rend="italics">Liquid Amber</name> in
     <lb/>to <placeName>Spaine</placeName>, inso much that they do bring many pipes, and
     <lb/><choice><orig>Barelles</orig><reg>Barrels</reg></choice> full thereof to sell for Merchaundise, for heere
     <lb/>they raise profite thereof, to perfume in thinges of sweete
 <pb/>
     <lb/>smelles, wafting it in place of <name rend="italics">Storax</name>, for that the smoke
     <lb/>and smell deoth seeme to be the same: and also they doe put it
     <lb/>into other confections of sweete smelles to burne, and suche
     <lb/>like thinges. It casteth from it so much smell without bur-
     <lb/>ning of it, that wheresoever it be, it cannot be hidden, but
     <lb/>doth penetrate many houses and streets with the sweete
     <lb/>smell, when there is quantity of it.</p>
  <p>It serveth much in medicine, &amp; doth therein greate effect,
     <lb/>for that it healeth, comforteth, dissolveth, and mittigateth
     <lb/>payne applied unto the Moulde of the heades by it selfe, or
     <lb/>migled with other thinges <hi rend="italics">Aromaticall</hi>, it doth comfort
     <lb/>the braines, and taketh away the paines of any manner of
     <lb/>griefe, proceeding of a coulde cause layed after the manner
     <lb/>of a playster thereunto, it doeth also mitigate, and take a-
     <lb/>way the paynes, &amp;griefes or the stomacke, wherein it doth
     <lb/>a marvellous effect, applied after the maner of a Stoma-
     <lb/>cher. For that it doth comfort the Stomake, and doeth dis-
     <lb/>solve windes, and helpe digestion, and take away rawnesse
     <lb/>it causeth the meate to be well digested, it geveth lust to eate:
     <lb/>it is made of <name rend="italics">Liquide Amber</name>, spreade abroade upon a sheeps
     <lb/>skinne, in the forme of a breastplate, mindled with a little
     <lb/><name rend="italics">Storax</name>, <name rend="italics">Amber</name> and <hi rend="italics">Muske</hi>, it is a Playster which doeth
     <lb/>profite muche in all that I have sayed. There is knowne of
     <lb/>this playster very great experience, in this citie, for the
     <lb/>good effect that it worketh: it is hot in the ende of the second
     <lb/>degree, but moyst in the first. </p>
  <p>Out of this <name rend="italics">Liquid Amber</name>, is taken the Oyle that is cal-
     <lb/>led the oyle of <name rend="italics">Liquide Amber</name>, the which in his smel is more
     <lb/>sweet, it it taken out ot the <name rend="italics">Liquide Amber</name> when it is newly
     <lb/>gathered, putting it in parte where it may distill of it selfe,
     <lb/>(the more subtill) is the perfectest and best of all.</p>
  <p>Others there be that do presse it, because the more quan-
     <lb/>titie thereof may be taken out, &amp;they bring it for merchaun-
     <lb/>dise, for that that use to dresse Gloves therwith for the com-
     <lb/>mon people, and in this trade there is much spent.</p>
  <pb/>
  <p>It is used in Medicine for many diseases, and it is of
     <lb/>greate vertue to heale colde diseases, for it healeth excellent-
     <lb/>ly well al partes wheresoever it be applied, it dissolveth and
     <lb/>mollisieth any maner of hardnes, taking away the paynes:
     <lb/>it dissolveth the hardnesse of the Mother, and openeth the o-
     <lb/>pilations thereof. It provoketh the Monethly course in wo-
     <lb/>men, and it maketh soft any maner of hard thing. It is hotte
     <lb/>welneere in the third degree.</p>
  <p>And it is to be noted, that many doe bring this Storax
     <lb/>very thin from the Indias, which is not so good, for because
     <lb/>that they make it of the bowes of the trees, cut in pieces,
     <lb/>and sodden, and they gather the fatnes that swimmeth upon:
     <lb/>and the Indians doe sell the buddes of the rees whereout the
     <lb/>Liquid Amber is taken, made in handfulles, &amp; doe sell it in
     <lb/>their market places, for to put amongst their clothes, which 
     <lb/>causeth them to smell, as of the water of Angels, &amp; for this
     <lb/> purpose the Spaniards doe use it.</p> </div>
  <div type="subsection"><head rend="italics">Of the Balsamo.</head>
  <p>The doe bring from the <placeName>newe Spayne</placeName> that licour
     <lb/>most excellent, which for his excellencie and mervel-
     <lb/>lous effects, is called <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name>, and imitation of the
     <lb/>true <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name>, that was in the land of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and for
     <lb/>that it doeth such great workes, and remedie so many infir-
     <lb/>mities, there was geven to it such a name. It is made of a
     <lb/>tree greater than a <choice><orig>Powngarnet</orig><reg>Pomegranate</reg></choice> Tree, it carrieth leaves
     <lb/>like to Nettles: the Indians doe call it <name rend="italics">Xilo</name>, and we doe call
     <lb/>the same <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name>. It is made two maner of waies, the one
     <lb/>is by the way of incision, cutting the rynd of the Tree, which
     <lb/>is thinne, geving many small cuttinges, out of the which
     <lb/>there commeth a clammish licour, of colour white, but it
     <lb/>is little and moste excellent, and very perfect. The other fa-
     <lb/>shion is, whereby the Indians doe use too take out licour of
  <pb/>
     <lb/>the trees, which is a common use amongst them is this: they
     <lb/>take the bowes and the great peeces of the trees, and make
     <lb/>them as small, as they can, and then craft them into a greate
     <lb/>kettle, with a good quantity of water, &amp; so boyle them untill
     <lb/>they see it sufficiently done, and afterwarde they let it coole,
     <lb/>and gather up the oyle that doeth swimme thereuppon with
     <lb/>certayne shelles, and that is the <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name> that commeth too
     <lb/>these partes, and that commonly is used: the colour therof is
     <lb/>Alborne, which is likened to blacke, it is of most sweet smel,
     <lb/>and very excellent. It is not convenient, nor it ought to bee
     <lb/>kept in any other vessel then in silver (Glasse or <choice><orig>Tinne</orig><reg>Tin</reg></choice>, or a-
     <lb/>ny other thing glassed, it doeth penitrate and doeth passe 
     <lb/>through:) the use thereof is onely in thinges apperteining 
     <lb/>to Medicine, and it hath been used of long time, well neere
     <lb/>since the <placeName>new Spaine</placeName> was discovered, for that incontinent the
     <lb/>Spaniards had knowledge of it, because they did heale
     <lb/>therewith the woundes that they did receive of the Indians,
     <lb/>being advised of the vertue thereof by the same Indians, and
     <lb/>they did see the saide Indians heale and cure themselves
     <lb/>therewith.</p>
  <p>When it first came into <placeName>Spayne</placeName>, it was esteemed as
     <lb/>much as it was reason it shoulde be, for that they did see it
     <lb/>make mervellous woorkes, one ownce was woorth tenne <!-- look back into this (is the element num right to use for numbers that are written out" - Let's not worry about using num here -S -->
     <lb/>Duccates and upwardes, and now it is better cheape: the
     <lb/>first time that they carried it to Rome, it came to be woorth
     <lb/>one ounce, one hundreth Duccats: &amp; after that they brought <!-- same num question here -->
     <lb/>so much and such greate quantity, that it is nowe of small va-
     <lb/>lue: this commeth of the abundance of thinges. And when
     <lb/>it was very deere all men tooke profite of the profite of it,
     <lb/>and since it came to bee of so lower a price, it is not so
     <lb/>much esteemed beeyng the selfe same <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name>, that it
     <lb/>was then when it was woorth on hundreth Duccates <!-- "" -->
     <lb/>the ounce. Surely if the Indias had not beene disco-
     <lb/>vered, but onely for the effects, to send us this mervellous
     <lb/>licour, the labour had been wel employed which our Spani-
  <pb/>
     <lb/>ardes have taken for that the <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name> that was used to be
     <lb/>had in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, it is many yeeres since it failed, because the
     <lb/>Vine from whence it came, dried by, wherby you have now
     <lb/>none in the worlde. Our Lorde God did thinke it good in <!-- the Lord god comment. Answered in google doc -S -->
     <lb/>place of that geve us this <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name>, of the <placeName>newe Spayne</placeName>,
     <lb/>the which in my iudgement in Medicinal vertue, is no <choice><orig>whie</orig><reg>way</reg></choice>
     <lb/>inferior unto that of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, accroding to the great effects
     <lb/>that we doe see in it, and the great profite that it doeth, which
     <lb/>we doe see in Medicines, in three wayes: that is to say, it is
     <lb/>taken at the mouth, or it is applied outwardly, or it serveth
     <lb/>in thinges of Surgery. Taken in the morning fasting, it 
     <lb/>healeth the shortnesse of breath: it taketh away the diseases
     <lb/>of the bladder: it provoketh the <choice><orig>Menstrues</orig><reg>Menstruation</reg></choice> of Women taken
     <lb/>and applied with a Pessary: it taketh away the olde paynes
     <lb/>of the stomacke, licking certayne droppes therof in the mor-
     <lb/>ning fasting, layde upon the palme of the hande, and so con-
     <lb/>tinued: it doeth comforte the stomacke: it doeth rectify the
     <lb/>Liver: it maketh a good colour in the face, it maketh a good
     <lb/>breathing, it openeth the Breast, it undoeth opilations, and
     <lb/>conserveth youth. I know a person of much estimation that
     <lb/>did use it, and beeyng of great yeers, did looke like a young
     <lb/>man, and lived after he used it without occasion of any evill.
     <lb/>They which have been troubled with a dry cough have u-
     <lb/>sed it, and to some it hath beene profitable, and some Gen-
     <lb/>tle women that have not brought foorth Children, have u-
     <lb/>sed it in tentes for too purge the Mother, and it hath done
     <lb/>them good.</p>
  <p>It hath beene also applyed outwardly in all manner of
     <lb/>griefes caused of coulde humours, or of windes. For that
     <lb/>beyng continued, it taketh away very well any manner of
     <lb/>griefe, applied hot, with a little fether, and laying there-
     <lb/>upon a cloth wet with the selfe same <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name>, it is dissolva-
     <lb/>tive, and so it doeth consume and undoe swellinges colde
     <lb/>and olde. It strengtheneth any part where it is put unto,
     <lb/>the foreparte of the heade it doeth comforte mervellously,
  <pb/>  
     <lb/>and taketh away the paynes thereof, consuming any man-
     <lb/>ner of humour or colde that is in it: taketh away the pal-
     <lb/>sey by annoynting the foreheade and Necke, and the
     <lb/>partes that bee impotent, and it doeth profite in all in-
     <lb/>firmities of Sinewes, and shrinkinges of them. Applied
     <lb/>unto the stomacke, it helpeth digestion, and comforteth it,
     <lb/>dissolving windinesse: and if there bee any opilation, it o-
     <lb/>peneth it. And also the opilations of the inner partes it
     <lb/>doeth mollifie and soften: it taketh away the payne of the
     <lb/>Stone in the kidneies or <choice><orig>Raynes</orig><reg>Pains</reg></choice>, beyng layde hot uppon
     <lb/>the grieved place: in the paynes of the Bellie or Sto-
     <lb/>macke caused of colde or wyndes, beeyng put thereunto hot,
     <lb/>or layed uppon hotte Breade taken out of the Oven, it ta-
     <lb/>keth them away, it provoketh Urine, and them that cannot
     <lb/>pisse, applying it outwardly, and taking a fewe drops
     <lb/>thereof, it doeth unloose and expelleth it: in the paynes
     <lb/>of the <choice><orig>ioyntes</orig><reg>joints</reg></choice> it hath mervellous effect, and in these it hath
     <lb/>a speciall Perogative, and especially in the <name rend="italics">Sciatica</name>, dis-
     <lb/>solveth any manny of hardnesse or swelling that remay-
     <lb/>neth in any such griefe: in paynes of the Sinowes it is a
     <lb/>mervellous remedie, and in all runninges of fluxe, it doeth
     <lb/>stoppe and heale. </p>
 <p>This <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name> being applied in practice of Surgery hath
    <lb/>great effects, of it selfe, or mingled any other way with me-
    <lb/>edicine, that hath vertue to doe the effect whersoever it is ap-
    <lb/>plied, and to shew all the vertues thereof, it would be verye
    <lb/>long. I do remit it to him that shall use it, that he may make
    <lb/>they myxture that shall be necessary and convenient.</p>
 <p>The <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name> is a verye common and used remedie for
    <lb/>woundes being newe, for that it doth cure them by the first
    <lb/>intention, gleweing together the partes without making
    <lb/>matter, and where there be bruses that cannot be glewed
    <lb/>together, it doeth a verye good worke, makyng dige-
    <lb/>stion with readinesse, and in the rest of the workes that
    <lb/>appertaine to Surgerie, it doth that which is convenient
 <pb/>
    <lb/>untill the woundes be whole, and for this cause the use ther-
    <lb/>of is a common medicine in all sergery for poore folkes, see-
    <lb/>ing that as with one medicine all effectes are wrought there-
    <lb/>with, that are necessary: &amp;it is a common thing to say, that
    <lb/>when one is hurt, let <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name> be put thereunto, and so they
    <lb/>doe, &amp; it doth heale them. In the woundes of Sinewes it
    <lb/>woorketh a mervellous effect, for that it doeth cure &amp;
    <lb/>heale. It healeth better then any other medicine doeth, it re-
    <lb/>sisteth colde, the woundes of the head it healeth very well, not
    <lb/>having the Skull broken, not perished.</p>
 <p>Any manner of woundes bbeyng freshe it doeth heale in
    <lb/>any parte of the dodie wheresoever they bee, so that there
    <lb/>be no more in it but a simple wounde. In <choice><orig>ioyntes</orig><reg>joints</reg></choice> what
    <lb/>manner of woundes soever it bee, it doeth make a marvel-
    <lb/>lous woorke: The use thereof is very common in this Ci-
    <lb/>tie, in woundes. For that you have fewe houses, but you
    <lb/>have <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name> in them for this effect, so that in wounding of
    <lb/>any person foorthwith they goe to the <name rend="italics">Balsamo</name>, for with lit-
    <lb/>tle quantities thereof they do cure and heale, and many
    <lb/>times with putting of it once every thirde day, they finde
    <lb/>the woundes whole. In olde sores applied by it selfe, or with
    <lb/>any other oyntment, it doeth mundifie, and fill them uppe
    <lb/>with fleshe.</p>
 <p>In large fevers <name rend="italics">Paroxismales</name> beyng layde halfe an houre
    <lb/>before the colde doeth come, uppon the moulde of the heade
    <lb/>very hot, the patient being very well covered with clothes,
    <lb/>and taking forthwith five or sixe droppes thereof in wine, it
    <lb/>taketh away the colde, in three or foure times doing it. It is
    <lb/>of a sharpe savour and somewhat bitter, whereby are seen the
    <lb/>dry partes and comfortative that it hath: it is hot and dry in
    <lb/>the second degree.</p>
 <p>I will not let to write of a certayne Hearbe, which the
    <lb/>Conquerours of the <placeName>newe Spaine</placeName> doe use for the remedy of
    <lb/>their wounds, and shottes of arrowes, which unto them was
    <lb/>a great remedie in their troubles, and it was discovered by
 <pb/>
    <lb/>an Indian, which was Servant too a Spaniarde called
    <lb/><persName>John Infant</persName>. He was the first that used it, they did call it,
    <lb/>and doe call it at this present day, the <name>Hearbe of John In-
    <lb/>fant</name>: this hearbe is little, they gather it greene, and beate
    <lb/>it, and so they lay it simply upon the wound: it doth restraine
    <lb/>and stoppe the blood, and if it be a wounde in the fleshe, it
    <lb/>doth cause it to growe together, and healeth it by glewing
    <lb/>the partes. The woundes of the Sinewes, and other
    <lb/>partes it doth comfort, mundifie, and ingendreth flesh in them
    <lb/>untill they be whole, and because they doe not find this hearb
    <lb/>in all places, they bring it made into pouder, for that it
    <lb/>woorketh the same effect as well as being greene, and the 
    <lb/>pouder, as some say, doth it better than the hearbe.</p>
 <p>As this hearbe, so likewise have you many other in all
    <lb/>the other partes of the <placeName>Indias</placeName>, that have the same and other
    <lb/>properties &amp; doe woorke mervellous effects: and to write of
    <lb/>every one of them particularly, it were needefull to make a
    <lb/>greater volume, then wee doe pretende of this that we shall
    <lb/>entreate of.</p>
<p>Three thinges they bring from our <placeName>Occidentall Indi-
   <lb/>as</placeName>, which at this day bee celebrated in all the worlde, and
   <lb/>with them they have made &amp; doe make the greatest workes
   <lb/>that ever were made in medicine, &amp; there were never the like
   <lb/>made, by any other medicine that unto this day hath beene
   <lb/>knowen, for that the nature of al three is to cure infirmities,
   <lb/>which without this remedy be incurable, and to woorke the
   <lb/>effectes that doe seeme to bee thinges of woonder, and these
   <lb/>are notorious, not onely in these parts, but in all the worlde:
   <lb/>the which thinges are the wood that is called <name rend="italics">Guaiacan</name>, the
   <lb/><name rend="italics">China</name> and the <name rend="italics">Sarcaparillia</name>. And for that it seemeth that
   <lb/>the <name rend="italics">China</name> doth come from <placeName>Portingall</placeName>, and that the portin-
   <lb/>gales doe bring it from their <placeName>Orientall Indias</placeName>, and not from
   <lb/>ours, I willsay what it to be said herafter when we do speak
   <lb/>thereof. And therefore let us beginne with <name rend="italics">Guaiacan</name>, as of
   <lb/>a remedie that first came from the <placeName>Indias</placeName>, and as first of the
<pb/>
   <lb/>best of all, as exprience hath shewed, and the use thereof in
   <lb/>so many yeares.
</p></div>
<div type="subsection"><head rend="italics">Of the Guaiacan and of the holie Wood.</head>
<p><hi rend="DIC">T</hi>he <name rend="italics">Guaiacan</name>, that is called the wood of
   <lb/>the <placeName>Indias</placeName> was discovered forthwith, when
   <lb/>the first <placeName>Indias</placeName> were found, which was the
   <lb/>Island of <placeName rend="italics">Sancto Domingo</placeName>, where is great
   <lb/>quantity thereof. There was an Indian
   <lb/>that gave knowledge thereof to his Mai-
   <lb/>ster, in this maner. Ther was a Spaniard
   <lb/>that did suffer great paines of the Poxe, which he had taken
   <lb/>by the company of an Indian woman, but his servant being
   <lb/>one of the Phisitions of that countrie, gave unto him the wa-
   <lb/>ter of <name rend="italics">Guaiacan</name>, wherewith not onely his grievous paynes
   <lb/>were taken away that he did suffer, but he was healed verie
   <lb/>well of the evill: with the which many other Spaniardes,
   <lb/>that were infected with the same evill were healed also, the
   <lb/>which was communicated immediatly, with them that came
   <lb/>from thence, hither to <placeName rend="italics">Seuill</placeName>, and from thence it was divul-
   <lb/>ged throughout all <placeName>Spaine</placeName>, and from thence through all the
   <lb/>world, for that the infection was sowen abroade throughout
   <lb/>all partes thereof: and surely for this evill it is the best, &amp; the
   <lb/>most chieferemedy of as many hirtherto have been found,
   <lb/>and with most assurance, and most certentie, it healeth
   <lb/>and cureth the sayde disease, if they be wel handled: and this
   <lb/>water given as it ought to be, it is certaine that it healeth it
   <lb/>most perfectly, without turning to fall againe, except the
   <lb/>sicke man doe returne to tumble in the same bosome, where
   <lb/>be tooke the first infection.</p>
<p>Our Lord God would from whence the evill of the Poxe
   <lb/>came, form thence shoulde com ethe remedy for them. Since
   <lb/>it is knowne that they came into these parts from the Indi-
<pb/>
   <lb/>as, and first of all from <placeName rend="italics">Sancto Domingo.</placeName> The Poxe bee as
   <lb/>common amongest the Indians, and as familiare, as the
   <lb/>Measelles bee unto us, and well neere the most part of the
   <lb/>Indians, both men and women have them, wihtout making
   <lb/>thereof any scruple, and they came first in this sorte.</p>
<p>In the yeere of our Lorde God <date when="1493">1493</date>. in the <choice><orig>warres</orig><reg>wars</reg></choice>
   <lb/>that the Catholike King made in <placeName>Naples</placeName>, with <persName>King
   <lb/>Charles</persName> of <placeName>France</placeName>, that was called <persName>Great head</persName>, in this time
   <lb/>sir <persName>Christopher Colon</persName>, returned from the discoverie that hee
   <lb/>had made of the <placeName>Indias</placeName>, which was <placeName rend="italics">Sancto Domingo</placeName>, and o-
   <lb/>ther Islands, &amp; he brought with him from <placeName rend="italics">Sancto Domingo</placeName>,
   <lb/>a great number of Indians, both men and women, which
   <lb/>be carried with him to <placeName>Naples</placeName>, where the Catholike king
   <lb/>was at that tyme, who had then concluded the <choice><orig>warres</orig><reg>wars</reg></choice>, for
   <lb/>that there was peace betweene the twoo Kinges, and the
   <lb/>hostes did communicate together, the one with the other.
   <lb/>And <persName>Colon</persName> being come thither with his Indians, the most
   <lb/>part of them brought with them the fruit of their countrie,
   <lb/>which was the Poxe. And the Spaniardes began to have
   <lb/>conversation with the Indian women, in such sorte, that the
   <lb/>men and women of the Indias, did infect the campe of the
   <lb/>Spaniardes, Italians, and Almaines, for the Catholike
   <lb/>king had then of all these Nations, and there were many
   <lb/>that were infected with the evill. And after the hostes com-
   <lb/>moned together, the fire did kindle in the campe of the king
   <lb/>of <placeName>France</placeName>, of which it folowed, that in short tyme the one
   <lb/>and the other were infected with this evill seede: and from
   <lb/>thence it hath spred abrode into all the worlde.</p>
<p>
   <lb/>At the beginning it had diverse names: the Spaniards
   <lb/>did thinke that it had beene given them by the French-
   <lb/>men, and they called it the <placeName>Frenche</placeName> evil. The Frenchmen
   <lb/>thought that in <placeName>Naples</placeName>, and by them of the Countrie, the
   <lb/>evill had beene given them, and they called it the evil of <placeName>Na-
   <lb/>ples</placeName>. And they of <placeName>Almaine</placeName> seing that by conversation with
   <lb/>the Spaniards, they came by it, they called it the Spa-
<pb/>
   <lb/>nishe Skabbe, and other called it the Measelles of the <placeName>In-
   <lb/>dias</placeName>, and that very truely, seing that from thence came the
   <lb/>evill in the beginning.</p>
<p>Amongest the great phisitions of that tyme, there were
   <lb/>sundry great opinions of the cause, and originall of the in-
   <lb/>firmitie. The one sort sayde that it came of the evil me-
   <lb/>lancholie meates, that the hostes of necessitie had eaten, as
   <lb/>wilde hearbes, and many gardeine hearbes, and rootes of
   <lb/>hearbes, asses, and horses, and other lyke things, that
   <lb/>ingender such lyke infirmities, corrupting and burnyng
   <lb/>the blood. Others there were, that did attribute it to the
   <lb/>coniunctions of Saturne and Mars, and they did apply it
   <lb/>to the heavenly influence, and gave thereuntoo <choice><orig>divers</orig><reg>diverse</reg></choice> and
   <lb/>sundrynames. Some called it the Leprosie, others Swine
   <lb/>Poxe, other Mentegra, others the Deathly evill, others
   <lb/>Elephansia, without certaine assurance that disease it
   <lb/>was. For they were ignoraunt that it was a newe disease,
   <lb/>and they woulde reduce it to some already knowen and writ-
   <lb/>ten of. And nowe we come to our <name rend="italics">Guaiacan</name>, whose name
   <lb/>was given by the Indians, and of them very well knowen,
   <lb/>and so they have called it and do call it, in all the world, cal-
   <lb/>ling it also the woodde of the <placeName>Indias</placeName>. Of this woodde ma-
   <lb/>ny have written and much, one sort sayeng that it was <name rend="italics">eba-
   <lb/>no</name>, others that it was a kinde of Boxe, with many other
   <lb/>names wherby they have named it. It is a new tree and ne-
   <lb/>ver seene in our partes, nor in any other of the discoveries, &amp;
   <lb/>as the country is newe, so is the tree a newe thing also.</p>
<p>Whatsoever it be, it is a  great tree, of the greatnesse of
   <lb/>an Oke: it casteth out many bowes, the einde it doth cast
   <lb/>from it being dry, greate, and full of Gumme, the hart
   <lb/>thereof is very greatm it is well neere lyke to blacke, all is
   <lb/>very hard as much and more then <name rend="italics">Ebano</name> is. It casteth forth
   <lb/>a little leafe and hard, and every yeere it bringeth foorth yel-
   <lb/>low flowers, out of the which is ingendered a round fruite,
   <lb/>with litle kernelles within it, of the greatnesse of a Medler:
<pb/>
   <lb/>of these Trees there is greate aboundance in <placeName rend="italics">Sancto Do-
   <lb/>mingo.</placeName></p>
<p>And after this they have founde an other Tree, of the
   <lb/>kind of this <name rend="italics">Guaiacan</name>, in <placeName>Saint John de <placeName rend="italics">Puerto Rico</placeName></placeName>, which
   <lb/>is an other islande neere to that of <placeName rend="italics">Sancto Domingo</placeName>, such an
   <lb/>other tree as that is, saving that it is lesse, &amp; the body of the
   <lb/>tree and the bowes are smaller, &amp; it hath scarcely any harte,
   <lb/>or if it have any, it is very little, and htat is in the body of the
   <lb/>tree, for that the bowes have none at all: It is of more sweete
   <lb/>smel and more bitter then the <name rend="italics">Guaiacan</name>, that is now used in
   <lb/>our tyme, I meane that of <placeName rend="italics">Sancto Domingo</placeName>, and for his mar-
   <lb/>vellous effects, they called it the holy Woode, &amp;surely with
   <lb/>reason: for that it is of a better working then that of <placeName rend="italics">Sancto
   <lb/>Domingo</placeName>, which is seene by experience, but even aswell the
   <lb/>one &amp; the other is a marvellous remedy, to cure the disease
   <lb/>of the Poxe: of the which and of every one of them a wa-
   <lb/>ter is made, and is taken for this infirmitie, and for many
   <lb/>others in this forme.</p>
<p>They take twelve ounces of the wood made small, and
   <lb/>twoo ounces of the Rinde of the same wooddee broken, and
   <lb/>they cast it to steepe in three pottels of Water, in a newe
   <lb/>pot, that will holde somwhat more, for the space of <num>XXiiii</num>.
   <lb/>houres: and the pot being well stopt, they seeth it over a soft
   <lb/>fire of kindles Coales, untill the twoo Pottels bee sodde a-
   <lb/>way, and one remayning. And this is to be noted at the time
   <lb/>the water is put to it, putting there in one Pottle, they dip
   <lb/>in a little Rodde, and doe marke howe high the water of
   <lb/>one Pottle reacheth, and by that measure and marke they
   <lb/>shall see when the twoo are sodde away, and the one Pottell
   <lb/>remayneth. After the water is sodden, they set it to coole, &amp;
   <lb/>straine it, and keepe it in a glasses vessel, and forthwith up-
   <lb/>pon the said sodden woodde, they poure foure pottels of wa-
   <lb/>ter, and seeth it till on bee sodden away, and this water
   <lb/>must be strayned and kept apart, and it must bee taken in
   <lb/>this forme. </p>
<pb/>
<p>After that the sicke man is purged by the counsell of a
   <lb/><choice><orig>phisition</orig><reg>physician</reg></choice>, let him be put into a warme Chamber, and kept
   <lb/>from the colde and from ayre, and beeing laied in his bedde,
   <lb/>let him take early in the morning tenne ounces of Water, 
   <lb/>of that which was first made wel warmed, and let him bee
   <lb/>covered so that her may sweate wel, &amp; let him kepe his sweat
   <lb/>at the least two houres, &amp; after he hath swet, let him be made
   <lb/>cleane from his sweat, &amp; take a warme shirt, and the rest of
   <lb/>his linen clothes, &amp; foure houres after he hath swette, let
   <lb/>him eate Reasings, Almonds, and Bisket, and that in reaso-
   <lb/>nable quantitie. Then let him drinke of the water that was
   <lb/>made at the second tyme, the quantity that he hath need of
   <lb/>and of the selfe same let him drinke in the day time, &amp; eight
   <lb/>houres after he hath eaten, let him returne to take the first
   <lb/>water, and let him take other tenne ounces well warmed,
   <lb/>and then sweate other twoo houres, and after his sweate let
   <lb/>him bee made cleane, and then bee covered againe with
   <lb/>warme cloathes, and one houre after hee hath swet, let him
   <lb/>make his supper of the same Reasings, Almonds, and Bis-
   <lb/>ket, and drinke of the second Water. This order he must ob-
   <lb/>serve the first fiftiene daies, except hee have some notable
   <lb/>weaknesse, and in such case hee must be succoured with ge-
   <lb/>ving him to eate of a young Chicken, <choice><orig>iointly</orig><reg>jointly</reg></choice>, with the rest of
   <lb/>the Diet: and in them that be leane, that cannot beare for pre-
   <lb/>cise Diet, it is sufficient that they take it for nine dayes, and 
   <lb/>at the end of them they may eate a little Chicken rosted, &amp; if
   <lb/>in a case the sicke person be <choice><orig>debilited</orig><reg>debilitated</reg></choice>, and that he cannot suf-
   <lb/>fer the Diet, let him have from the beginning a very small
   <lb/>Chicken, going forwarde increasing in the proces of tyme,
   <lb/>and beeing past the <num>15</num>. dayes, let him return to purge
   <lb/>himselfe at the sixtiene dayes end, &amp;let him take to the waight
   <lb/>of five shillinges of the substaunce of <name rend="italics">Canafistola</name>, taken out
   <lb/>by Strayner or other thing respondent thereunto, and
   <lb/>that day let him drinke no strong water, but of the simple,
   <lb/>and the next day after the Purgation, let him return to
<pb/>
   <lb/>the aforesayde order, taking in the morning and evening
   <lb/>the strong water with his sweatinges, and eating and drin-
   <lb/>king the same. Saving that in place of a Chicken hee
   <lb/>may eate halfe a rosted Pullet, or somwhatmore, and
   <lb/>this seconde tyme let him take it for other <num>xx</num>. daies, in the
   <lb/>which tyme hee may ryse, and walke about his chamber,
   <lb/>being apparelled and kept warme. And at the end of them,
   <lb/>hee shall returne to purge himselfe an other tyme, and
   <lb/>must have a speciall care to keepe good order, and after hee
   <lb/>hath taken the water for other fortie dayes, must keepe him-
   <lb/>selfe from women and from wyne especially: and in place
   <lb/>of wyne, he must drinke the simple water of the woodde,
   <lb/>which if he will not doe, then let him drinke of water sodden
   <lb/>with Anise seede or Fenell seede, supping little at night and
   <lb/>eating no flesh.</p>
<p>This is the best way that the water of the wood ought
   <lb/>to be taken, which doeth heale many infirmities incurable,
   <lb/>where other Medicines could not worke the same effect, &amp;
   <lb/>this water is the best remedy that is in the worlde, to heale
   <lb/>the disease of the Poxe, whatsoever or what kinde soe-
   <lb/>ver it bee, for that it rooteth it out for ever without any
   <lb/>more comming againe, and in this it hath his principal pre-
   <lb/>rogative and excellencie. This water is also good for the
   <lb/>Dropsy, for the shortnes of breath, for the Falling sicknes,
   <lb/>for the diseases of the Bladder, and of the Rayne, for the
   <lb/>payne of the Joynts, for all evils caused of cold humours,
   <lb/>for <choice><orig>ventositie</orig><reg>ventosity</reg></choice>, and other dangerous and importunate disea-
   <lb/>ses, where the ordinary benefites of <choice><orig>Phisicions</orig><reg>Physicians</reg></choice> have not pro-
   <lb/>fited. Chiefly it excelleth where the evil dispositions be, that
   <lb/>have proceeded at any tyme from the disease of the Poxe. 
   <lb/>There be many that with this woode have made sundry mix-
   <lb/>tures, making Syropes therof, and surely with good effect.
   <lb/>But my iudgement and opinion is, that he which shall take
   <lb/>the water of the wood, ought ot take it in the maner as is a-
   <lb/>above said, without any mingling thereof, for that by expe-
<pb/>
   <lb/>perience it hath beene seene so to make the better woorke.
   <lb/>This water is good for the teeth, making them white, and
   <lb/>fastning them, by continual washing of them therewith: it is
   <lb/>hot and dry in the second degree.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection"> <head rend="italics">Of the <name>China</name>.</head>
   <p><hi rend="DIC">T</hi>he Second Medicine that commeth from our In-
      <lb/>dias, is a roote called the <name rend="italics">China</name>. It seemeth that I
      <lb/>should slaunder it, to say that the <name rend="italics">China</name> groweth in
      <lb/>our Ocidental <placeName>Indias</placeName>, since commonly the portin-
      <lb/>gales doe bring it from the Orientall <placeName>Indias</placeName>.
      <lb/>By this you shall understande, that <persName>Syr Frauncis <hi rend="italics">de
      <lb/>Mendosa</hi></persName>, a worthy knight, when hee came from the <placeName>newe
      <lb/>Spayne</placeName> and <placeName>Peru</placeName>, shewed to mee a greate Roote, and
      <lb/>other little rootes, who asked mee, what rootes they were?
      <lb/>I aunswered that they were rootes of the <name rend="italics">China</name>, but that
      <lb/>they seemed to mee to bee very freshe. Hee sayde to mee,
      <lb/>that so they were, and that it was not longe since that
      <lb/>they had beene gathered and brought from the <placeName>newe Spaine</placeName>.
      <lb/>I narveled that they had it there, for I did beleeve that in
      <lb/>the <name rend="italics">China</name> only it had growen: he said unto mee, that not only
      <lb/>there was in the <placeName>newe Spaine</placeName> the <name rend="italics">China</name>, but that also wee
      <lb/>shoulde see brought greate quantitie of Spicerie from the
      <lb/>place which that <name rend="italics">China</name> came from. And I beleved it when
      <lb/>I saw the contract that he made with his <choice><orig>maiestie</orig><reg>majesty</reg></choice>, to bring
      <lb/>into <placeName>Spain</placeName> great quantitie of spicerie, that hee had begon
      <lb/>to set and to plante, and I saw greene Ginger brought from
      <lb/>thence, as also the <name rend="italics">China</name>. </p>
   <p>This <name rend="italics">China</name> is a roote lyke to the roote of a cane with
      <lb/>certaine knottes within it, whyte and some with the whyte-
      <lb/>nesse hath an alborne colour: it is red without, the best is
      <lb/>the freshest, that which hath no holes, if it bee weightie,
      <lb/>and not worme eaten, and that it have a fatnes as it were
      <lb/>congeled, and it hath an unsavery tast. This Roote doeth
  <pb/>
      <lb/>growe in the <name rend="italics">China</name>, which is the Orientall <placeName>Indias</placeName> neere
      <lb/>to <placeName rend="italics">Siria</placeName> and <placeName rend="italics">Sirciana</placeName>. It groweth neere to the Sea, onely
      <lb/>with the roote they helpe themselves, with the which the
      <lb/>Indians bee healed of grievous diseases. And therfore they
      <lb/>have it in great estimation: they do heale al maner of large
      <lb/>disease therewith: and also the shape diseases: especially
      <lb/>Agues, with the Water of it, provoking Sweats, and
      <lb/>by this way they heale many. It provoketh marvel-
      <lb/>lously.</p>
 <p>It is wel neere xxx. yeeres since that the Portingales
    <lb/>brought it to these parts with great estimation, for to heale al
    <lb/>manner of diseases, and especially the disease of the Poxe, in
    <lb/>the which it hath wrought greate effectes, and the Water is
    <lb/>given in this forme.  
 </p>
   



   


  

   
   


 
 </div>
 
 
  
     
  
     
     
     
 
      
     </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
